Ritali Ghosh

Curriculum Vitae

Graduate Student, Indian Institute of Science

ritalighosh@iisc.ac.in

https://www.ritalighosh.com/

C Last Updated: July 02nd 2024

I am a Graduate Student at the Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bengaluru, India. My research interests are in astrophysical fluid dynamics using computational techniques and cosmological simulations of galaxy formation. I am presently working on idealized simulations to understand the environmental influences on various components of the galaxy undergoing ram-pressure stripping.



Experience

2021-08 -Senior Research Fellow

Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, India Present

2019-08 -Junior Research Fellow

2021-07 Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, India



Education

2015-06 -Master of Science, Physics

2017-05 University of Calcutta, Kolkata, India

2012-06 -Bachelor of Science, Physics 2015-05 Bethune College, Kolkata, India



Publications

Ram pressure stripping in clusters: Gravity can bind the ISM but not the CGM, 2024 Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 531, Issue 3, July 2024, Pages 3445-3467 (doi:10.1093/mnras/stae1345)

Ritali Ghosh, Alankar Dutta, Prateek Sharma

Beyond profiles: Using log-normal distributions to model the multiphase circumgalactic medium, 2024

Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 531, Issue 4, July 2024, Pages 5117-5139 (doi:10.1093/mnras/stae977)

Alankar Dutta, Mukesh Singh Bisht, Prateek Sharma, Ritali Ghosh, Manami Roy and Biman B. Nath



Talks and Research Visits

Conference Talk, 7th ICM Theory & Computation Workshop, 2024 (online) 24 - 28 June 2024

organized by University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, USA

Conference Talk, Observe Local Think Global: What Solar Observations can teach us about Multiphase Plasmas across Astrophysical Scales, 2024

13 - 17 May 2024

organized at the International Space Science Institute at Bern, Switzerland

Conference Talk, Astronomical Society of India Meeting, ASI 2024

01-04 February 2024

organized by the Astronomical Society of India (ASI) at IISc, Bengaluru, India



Contact

Room D2-04, Department of Physical Science, Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, India – 560012

4 (+91) 7278335730

ritsg11@gmail.com

0000-0001-8643-7104

🄰 @RRitali

? RitaliG



Technical Profile

- Proficient in C/C++, Python, Fortran, LATEX
- Tools/Codes used: PLUTO. ParaView, Cloudy, yt
- Ability to Work in a Team
- Critical thinking and problem solving



Languages

English (proficient)

Hindi (native speaker)

Bengali (conversational)

German (A1 level)

Seminar Talk, Universitäts-Sternwarte München, Germany

November 2023

at Weekly CAST Meeting, USM, München, Germany

Seminar Talk, European Southern Observatory, Garching, Germany

November 2023

at CGM Meeting, ESO, Garching, Germany

Seminar Talk, In-house Symposium, Department of Physics, IISc

November 2023

at the annual symposium of Department of Physical Science, IISc, Bengaluru, India

Seminar Talk, Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, Garching, Germany

June 2023

MPA Galaxy Group Meeting, Garching, Germany

Conference Talk, Modelling of Multiphase Astrophysical Media, Aspenstein Castle at Lake Kochel, Bavaria

30 May - 02 June 2023

organized by Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, Garching, Germany

Conference Talk, GALFLOWS 2023: A National Workshop on Galactic inflows and outflows on all Scales, India

02 - 05 February 2023

organized by Inter University Campus of Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCAA), Pune

Poster Presentation, In-house Symposium, Department of Physics, IISc

February 2023

at the annual symposium of the Department of Physical Science, IISc, Bengaluru, India

Seminar Talk, Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, Garching, Germany

September 2022

MPA Cosmology Seminar, Garching, Germany

Seminar Talk, Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, INAF, Italy

September 2022

at INAF, the Italian National Institute for Astrophysics, Padua, Italy

Conference Talk, What matter(s) around galaxies 2022: Connecting the dots between the CGM and the larger-scale environment

12 - 16 September 2022

organized by Università Milano-Bicocca at Champoluc, Aosta Valley, Italy

Poster Presentation, Astronomical Society of India Meeting, ASI 2022

March 2022

organized by the Astronomical Society of India (ASI) at IIT Roorkee, India

KITP Program: Fundamentals of Gaseous Halos (online attendee)

January 2022

organized by Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics, Santa Barbara, California, USA



Academic Awards

National Level Qualified Examinations

- Qualified GATE Fellowship 2019
- Qualified UGC-JRF NET December 2018
- Qualified JEST 2019

Academic Achievements and Scholarships

- Ranked 5th in University of Calcutta, M.Sc. Batch 2015-17
- DST-INSPIRE Scholarship 2012-2017
- Mamraj Agarwal Rashtriya Puraskar, 2012 (felicitated for scoring 96.6% in CBSE Class XII Exams, 2012 by the then Governor of West Bengal, India)
- Certificate of Merit in Mathematics 2012 (for being in top 0.1% of All India Senior School Certificate Exam, 2012 in Mathematics (Score: 100%))

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistantship, Galaxies and the Interstellar Medium

January 2023 — May 2023

PH 365 course, Joint Astronomy and Astrophysics Program (JAP), Indian Institute of Science

Teaching Assistantship, Introduction to Fluid Mechanics and Plasma Physics

August 2021 — December 2021

PH 363 course, Joint Astronomy and Astrophysics Program (JAP), Indian Institute of Science



Professional activities and outreach

Reviewer, New Astronomy (ongoing)

Hands-on Sessions, Computational MHD with PLUTO (May 2023)

Organized hands-on sessions on basics of MPI parallel computation for about 60 beginning Ph.D. and advanced master's students in the Workshop on Computational MHD with the PLUTO code at IISc, Bangalore, India

Coordinator, Weekly arXiv Meetings (2021-22; 2022-23)

Coordinated the weekly arXiv meetings for the Astrophysics Group at the Department of Physics, IISc from 2021 to 2023

Volunteer, IISc Open Day (Feb 2020, Mar 2023, Feb 2024)

Actively participated in popular science lectures and hands-on demonstrations to around 50,000 people at the annual Open Day event at the IISc, Bangalore, India

Astronomy Outreach Volunteer, International Astronomical Union (2019)

Engaged with approximately 600 primary and high school students at Kendriya Vidyalaya IISc, Bangalore, India as a part of the International Astronomical Union (IAU) global project 'Astronomy Day in school'



Professional References

Prof. Prateek Sharma, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India

✓ prateek@iisc.ac.in

Dr. Max Gronke, Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, Garching, Germany

maxbg@mpa-garching.mpg.de